Finding Aid for First Baptist Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records, 1837-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
First Baptist Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records
1837-1991
First Baptist Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
86731 Ba 2
Ann Arbor, Michigan Baptist church established in 1828; church covenant, committee reports, annual reports, correspondence, financial records, membership rolls, treasurer's books, and scrapbooks; and records of church auxiliary organizations, including the Women's Society, the Baptist Students' Guild, and the Sunshine Circle of the International Order of King's Daughters and Sons.
17 linear feet
2 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was deposited by the church (Donor no. 927 ) in several accessions. The records of the Sunshine Circle were donated by Mrs. Sarah E. Stampfler (donor no. 4733 )
Additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The First Baptist Church of Ann Arbor, Michigan was organized May 10, 1828.
The records of the First Baptist Church of Ann Arbor document the life and activities of the church from its beginnings in 1828 to the early 1990s. The record group has been arranged into the following series: Covenant meetings; History / Background; Annual reports of church committees; Church archives: bulletins, annual reports, newsletters, and related materials; Church groups; Membership and other governance records; Financial records; Topical files; and Audio-Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Baptists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.MichiganAnn Arbor.; International Order of the King's Daughters and Sons. Sunshine Circle (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.; Women--Religious life--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; First Baptist Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Churches.; Baptist churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; First Baptist Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Stereographs.
- Covenant meetings
  - 1837-1847 (Box 1)
    (includes church covenant, 1837)
  - 1848-1862 (Box 1)
  - 1862-1906 (Box 1)
  - 1906-1948 (Box 1)
  - 1948-1978 (Box 1)
- History / Background
  - "History of the First Baptist Church, 1828-1928" by Mrs. Helen Beman (Box 1)
    (2 copies with variations)
  - Historic sketch of the First Baptist Church in Ann Arbor" by Andrew Ten Brook (Box 1)
  - Historical information concerning First Baptist Church, 1928-1938; 2 copies (Box 1)
  - Reports of church historians
    - Helen E. Beman, 1938-1939 (Box 2)
    - Mabel Waterman, 1939-1942 (Box 2)
    - Florence M. Bancroft, 1942-1950 (Box 2)
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Certificate of amendment to Articles of Association, 1923 (Box 2)
  - Specifications of new church building, undated (Box 2)
  - Church contracts, 1879-1882 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1865-1890 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1893-1939 (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea (Box 2)
- Annual reports of church committees, etc.
  - 1894-1942, 46 folders (Box 2)
- Church archives: bulletins, annual reports, newsletters, and related materials
  (Interspersed in this series are binders containing similar kinds of documents that were maintained by the church historian)
  - 1894-1935 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - 1940-1941 (Box 3)
  - 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - 1942-1943 (Box 3)
  - 1943-1944 (Box 3)
  - 1944, 1945 (Box 3)
  - 1945-1946 (Box 3)
  - 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - 1947-1948 (Box 3)
  - 1948-1949 (Box 3)
  - 1949-1950 (Box 3)
  - 1950-1951 (Box 3)
  - 1951-1952 (Box 3)
  - (church historian's records), 1951-1952 (Box 3)
  - 1952-1953 (Box 3)
  - (church historian's records), 1952-1953 (Box 3)
  - 1953-1954 (Box 4)
  - (church historian's records), 1953-1954 (Box 4)
  - 1954-1955 (Box 4)
  - (church historian's records), 1954-1955 (Box 4)
  - 1955 (Box 4)
  - (church historian's records), 1955 (Box 4)
  - 1956 (Box 4)
  - (church historian's records), 1956 (Box 4)
  - 1957 (Box 4)
  - (church historian's records), 1957 (Box 4)
  - (church historian's records), 1958 (Box 5)
  - (church historian's records), 1959 (Box 5)
  - (church historian's records), 1960 (Box 5)
  - (church historian's records), 1961 (Box 5)
  - (church historian's records), 1962 (Box 5)
  - (church historian's records), 1963 (Box 6)
  - 1964-1965 (Box 6)
  - 1966 (Box 6)
  - 1967 (Box 6)
  - 1968 (Box 6)
  - 1969 (Box 7)
  - 1970 (Box 7)
  - 1971 (Box 7)
  - 1972 (Box 7)
  - 1973 (Box 7)
  - 1974 (Box 7)
  - 1975 (Box 7)
  - 1976 (Box 8)
  - 1977 (Box 8)
  - 1978 (Box 8)
  - 1979 (Box 8)
  - 1980 (Box 8)
  - 1981 (Box 8)
  - 1982 (Box 8)
  - 1983 (Box 9)
  - 1984 (Box 9)
  - 1985 (Box 9)
  - 1986 (Box 9)
  - 1987 (Box 9)
  - 1988 (Box 9)
  - 1989 (Box 10)
  - 1990 (Box 10)
  - 1991 (Box 10)
- Church groups
  - University Young Men's Class
    - Secretary's book, 1905-1906 (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
  - Baptist Young People's Union
    - Record book, 1892-1900 (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
    - Account book, 1895-1911 (Box 10)
  - Student's Guild
    - Correspondence, 1910-1911 (Box 10)
    - Correspondence, 1912-1916 (Box 10)
    - Correspondence, 1917 (Box 10)
    - Reports, 1910-1915 (Box 10)
    - Reports, 1916-1918 (Box 10)
    - Reports, 1917-1918 (Box 10)
    - Reports, 1919 (Box 10)
    - Reports, 1920 (Box 10)
    - Reports, 1921-1927; undated (Box 10)
    - Reports and constitution, 1915-1916 (Box 10)
    - Reports, 1916-1917; 1917-1918 (Box 10)
    - Accounts (Box 10)
    - The Assimilator publication (Box 10)
    - Printed items (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous and loose clippings (perhaps intended for scrapbook), 1909-1911 (Box 10)
    - Scrapbook, 1913-1916 (Box 10)
    - Secretary's books
      - 1907-1917 (Box 11)
      - 1919-1922 (Box 11)
      - 1923-1924 (Box 11)
      - 1924-1928 (Box 11)
      - 1927-1928 (Box 11)
      - 1932-1937 (Box 11)
    - Accounts, 1909-1940 (Box 11)
    - Programs and Reports, 1902-1942 (Box 11)
  - Baptist Campus Foundation of Ann Arbor, Inc.
    - Articles of Incorporation and Bylaws (Box 11)
    - Budgets and financial reports, 1964-1980 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, 1935-1979; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Guild House Committee minutes, 1979 (Box 11)
    - Minutes, 1965-1979; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Promotion and Planning, 1961-1979 (Box 11)
    - Reports, 1965-1978 (Box 11)
    - Student Lists, 1938-1961 (Box 11)
    - Student Packet, 1977 (Box 11)
  - Roger Williams Guild, 1948-1958 (Box 11)
  - "A Study of student participation in Baptist religious activities at the University of Michigan ", 1947-1948 (Box 11)
    (study done by Lane Hall sociology of religion seminar)
  - Ladies Benevolent Society
    - Record book, 1875-1909 (Box 11)
      (volume also includes records of the Mite Society, 1863-1875)
    - Account book and membership list, 1875-1879 (Box 11)
  - Women's Society
    - Secretary's books
      - 1895-1919 (Box 11)
      - 1919-1928 (Box 11)
      - 1929-1938 (Box 11)
      - 1938-1944 (Box 11)
      - 1944-1949 (Box 11)
      - 1971-1977 (Box 12)
    - Treasurer's books
      - 1910-1936 (Box 12)
      - 1918-1922 (Box 12)
      - 1922-1927 (Box 12)
      - 1927-1936 (Box 12)
  - Women's Society, Group I
    - Records, 1918-1924 (Box 12)
  - Women's Society, Group II
    - Records, 1919-1926 (Box 12)
  - Woman's Missionary Society
    - Treasurer's book, 1914-1916 (Box 12)
  - Women's Association (formerly Women's Society)
    - Yearbooks, 1943-1955 (Box 12)
    - Annual Reports, 1983-1986 (Box 12)
  - Women's Society
    - Annual Reports
      - 1916-1942 (Box 12)
      - 1963-1980, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - History, Programs, and Circle Activities, 1928-1987 (Box 12)
    - Minutes (Delia Goodyear Circle), 1984-1985 (Box 12)
  - Adelphai Fellowship (formerly Mother's Club) (Box 12)
  - International Order of King's Daughters and Sons, Sunshine Circle
    The Sunshine Circle, though closely associated with the First Baptist Church, is not a formal church organization
    - Minutes
      - 1901-1909 (Box 12)
      - 1931-1938 (Box 12)
      - 1938-1943 (Box 12)
      - 1943-1950 (Box 12)
      - 1950-1958 (Box 12)
      - 1958-1959 (Box 13)
      - 1960-1966 (Box 13)
      - 1966-1969 (Box 13)
      - 1970-1975 (Box 13)
    - Treasurer's books
      - 1916-1930 (Box 13)
      - 1931-1943 (Box 13)
      - 1943-1960 (Box 13)
    - Miscellanea (Box 13)
    - Published: Bible (containing dedication) and History of the International Order of the King's Daughters and Sons by Sara F. Gugle (1931) (Box 13)
- Membership and other governance records
  - Membership registers
    - 1911-1917 (Box 13)
    - 1917-1924 (Box 13)
    - 1924-1942 (Box 13)
    - 1942-1953 (Box 13)
    - 1954-1964 (Box 13)
  - Board of Trustees
    - Minutes, 1871-1926 (Box 14)
    - Minutes 1881 and register and statistics, 1879-1888 (Box 14)
    - Correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 14)
    - Minutes, 1972-1974 (Box 14)
    - Minutes, 1975-1988; 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Board of Trustees minutes, 1990-1991 (Box 14)
  - Board of Deacons
    - Minutes, 1970-1974 (Box 14)
    - Minutes, 1971-1981 (Box 14)
    - Board of Deacons minutes, 1974; 1977; 1990-1991 (Box 14)
    - Deacons miscellaneous, 1971-1977 (Box 14)
  - Executive Council
    - Minutes, 1970-1981
      - 1970-1974 (Box 14)
      - 1975-1981 (Box 14)
    - Executive Council minutes, 1990-1991 (Box 14)
  - Board of Christian Education
    - Minutes, 1970-1974 (Box 14)
    - Minutes, 1976-1981 (Box 14)
    - Board of Christian Education minutes, 1977; 1990-1991 (Box 14)
- Financial records
  - Account books
    - 1874-1875 (Box 14)
    - 1881 (Box 14)
    - 1895-1900 (Box 14)
  - Benevolences, 1916-1917 (Box 14)
  - Communion and Poor Funds, 1884-1914 (Box 14)
  - Envelope collections, 1919-1920 (Box 14)
  - Financial ledger, 1924-1927 (Box 14)
  - Financial reports and budget, 1971-1973 (Box 15)
  - Receipts and accounts, 1874-1914
    - 1874-1880 (Box 15)
    - 1881-1914 (Box 15)
    - undated (Box 15)
  - Subscriptions
    - 1879-1882 (Box 15)
    - 1882 (Box 15)
    - 1883 (Box 15)
  - Sunday School records
    - 1871-1875 (Box 15)
    - 1878-1879 (Box 15)
    - 1915-1917 (Box 15)
  - Treasurer's book, 1885 (Box 15)
  - Treasurer's book, 1913-1917 (Box 15)
- Topical files
  - Agenda for the Nineties (Box 15)
  - American Baptist Campus Foundation (Guild House) minutes, 1972-1976 (Box 15)
  - Anniversaries
    - 100th Centennial Anniversary, 1928 (Box 15)
    - 125th Anniversary, 1953 (Box 15)
    - 150th Anniversary, 1978 (Box 15)
  - Boy Scouts. Rambler Troop, No. 14, Boy Scouts of America Miscellaneous (Box 15)
  - Budget/Financial Campaigns, 1946-1989 (Box 15)
  - Budget Committee, 1976-1980 (Box 15)
  - Burton (N.S.). Marriage register, 1867-1879 (Box 15)
  - By-laws (Box 15)
  - Campus Foundation 75th Anniversary, 1977 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence
    - Ruth Johnson, Church historian (1974-1982) (Box 15)
  - Day, Duane L. (associate pastor), papers concerning., 1955-1956 (Box 15)
  - Douglass House (Box 15)
  - History
    - Scrapbook, 1969-1971 (Volume 1)
    - Scrapbook, 1971-1978 (Volume 2)
    - Building and organ (Box 16)
    - Constitution (Box 16)
    - Ministers and members (Box 16)
  - Long-range Planning Committee
    - Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 16)
    - Minutes, 1970-1971 (Box 16)
  - Manual --H.N. Chute church manual, 1898 (Box 16)
  - Manuals, 1896; 1898; 1901; 1904; 1909-1910 (Box 16)
  - Membership Directories, 1914-1987 (scattered dates) (Box 16)
  - Membership lists, 1928-1946 (Box 16)
  - Membership (clippings about church members) (Box 16)
  - Membership cards (Box 16)
    (include name, address, and baptismal data)
  - Men's Club, 1944-1960 (Box 16)
  - Michigan Baptist Convention (correspondence), 1948-1962 (Box 16)
  - Mission Action Board, minutes, 1990-1991 (Box 16)
  - Missions Committee
    - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 16)
    - Minutes, 1968-1981 (Box 16)
  - Morikawa, Jitsuo (Box 16)
  - Music Committee minutes, 1970-1971 (Box 16)
  - Music (Box 16)
  - New Member materials (Box 16)
  - Nicaragua, 1986-1990; 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Nicaragua trip, 1989-1990; 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Pray, George (Box 16)
  - Programs, 1984-1990 (Box 16)
  - Refugee Resettlement, 1979-1980 (Box 16)
  - Search Committee correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 17)
  - Sermons
    - Dr. Chester H. Loucks (Box 17)
    - J.H. Middleton, 1960-1966 (Box 17)
    - Jitsuo Morikawa, 1981-1982 (Box 17)
    - Other, including O. Carroll Arnold and Robert Wallace, 1960-1986 (Box 17)
  - Specifications of the 3rd Ward Chapel (Box 17)
  - Specification for remodeling the heating plant (Box 17)
  - Student recommendations for membership (Box 17)
  - Sunday School Teachers' materials, 1980-1982 (Box 17)
  - Task Force on Seniors minutes, 1985 (Box 17)
  - Leroy Waterman lectures, 1963-1975; 3 folders (Box 17)
  - Vital records, 1828-1875 (Box 17)
    (incomplete; typescript, include marriage, death, baptisms, etc.)
  - Wallace, Rev. Robert
    - Reverend Robert Wallace (Box 17)
    - Sermons, 1986; 1988 (Box 17)
    - Questionnaire on Reverend Robert Wallace (Box 17)
  - Wallace, Peggy, Ordination, 1987-1990 (Box 17)
  - Waterman Lectureship correspondence, 1968-1976 (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous unprocessed: include bulletins, clippings, etc., 3 folders (Box 17)
- Audio-Visual Materials
  - Photographs
    - Church building and Guild (Douglass) House, 1885-1988 (Box 17)
    - Dr. Chester H. Loucks [et al] (Box 17)
    - Scrapbook of church history (Box 17)
      (compiled by Ruth Johnson, church historian; includes photographs of ministers and their families)
    - Church services and activities (Box 17)
    - Nicaraguan Trip Photographs, 1989-1990 (Box 17)
  - Sound Recordings
    - Tape of service on sermon by the Rev. James H. Middleton, November 26, 1967; 1/4 in. x 1200 ft.; 7" reel; silicone lubricated; 1.5 mil acetate backing; recorded at 3 3/4 ips (Box 17)
    - Audio cassette of the installation of Reverend Robert Wallace, 01/29/1984 (Box 17)